（新亞電影企業有限公司榮譽發行）
(Presented by New Asia Movie Co., Ltd.)
（改編：邱剛健、林琦然；副導：王瑜）
(Adaptation: CHIU Kang-chien and LIN Chi-jan//Assistant Director: WANG Yu)
（武術指導：陳全；助理：王慶良）
(Martial Arts Director: CHEN Chuan//Assistant: WANG Ching-liang)
（美術指導：顧毅；佈景：陳孝貴）
(Production Designer: KU Yi//Set Decorator: CHEN Hsiao-kuei)
（剪接：郭廷鴻；效果：哈都）
(Editor: KUO Ting-hung//Effects: HA Du)
（對白：金石）
(Dialogue: Chin Shih)
貓盜
Cat Bandit.
（封）
(Sealed)
（音樂、作曲：曾仲影）
(Music by TSENG Chung-ying)
（作詞：新芒；主唱：原野三重唱）
(Lyrics by Hsin Mang//Sung by The Plains Trio)
（配樂：黃茂山）
(Original Music by HUANG Mao-shan)
（攝影：廖慶松；燈光：金長樑）
(Cinematographer: LIAO Ching-sung//Lighting: CHIN Chang-liang)
（劇務：葉茂林；場記：高健峰）
(Production Manager: YEH Mao-lin//Script Supervisor: KAO Chien-feng)
（劇照：王富雄；特技：林洋次）
(Still Photographer: WANG Fu-hsiung//Stunts: LIN Yang-tzu)
（化妝：蕭幸美；服裝：孫志勇）
(Makeup: HSIAO Hsing-mei//Costume Design: SUN Chih-yung)
（梳妝：黃郁蘭；道具：胡廉璧；場務：林和平）
(Hair: HUANG Yu-lan; Props: HU Lien-pi//Production Assistant: LIN He-ping)
（主題歌：海山唱片公司發行）
(Theme Song Distributed by//Hai Shan Record Co., Ltd.)
（錄音：金都錄音公司；沖印：大都彩色沖印公司）
(Recording by Kin Du Recording Co., Ltd.//Printed by Da Du Color Prints)
（魯平飾衛天鵬）
(LU Ping as Wei Tien-peng)
貓盜
Cat Bandit...
我不信貓盜他們有多大的本事
I don’t believe that Cat Bandit
能帶著富貴神仙
can get out of the desert
呂三爺的三百萬兩黃金
with the three million taels of gold
走出這片沙漠
stolen from Lord Lu San.
放白信鴿傳書給呂三爺
Send a pigeon//to deliver the message to Lord Lu San
報告黃金被劫
that his gold was stolen.
想不到我呂三真是流年不利
I, Lu San, has the worst of luck.
（張冲飾呂三）
(CHANG Chung as Lu San)
獨生兒子被殺
My only son was killed.
現在居然有人
And now someone
敢搶我那三百萬兩黃金
stole my gold too.
獨孤痴
Tu-ku Chih?
（張翔飾獨孤痴）
(CHANG Hsiang as Tu-ku Chih)
傳書拉薩城胡大掌櫃
Send a message to Shopkeeper Hu in Lhasa.
殺我兒子的
Nobody will kill
任何人都不准殺他
whoever killed my son.
我要讓他也嘗嘗喪子之痛
I’ll make him lose his son too.
被搶的黃金
And the stolen gold
不管用什麼方法都要找回來
must be retrieved at any cost.
#烈日當空
#The scorching sun high up
#征程茫茫
#The journey ahead unknown
#大地一飛鷹，重重越關山
#An eagle is flying over the mountains
#滿天風沙
#Blowing sand everywhere
#長途流浪
#Roving about endlessly
#不知天涯在何方
#Never know where I belong
我們還有好多事要做
#We have a lot of work to do.
（王冠雄飾小方）
(WANG Kuan-hsiung as Fang)
你們總算等到了
You’ve got me finally.
（凌雲飾卜鷹）
(Ling Yun as Pu Ying)
好劍
A good sword.
你喜歡，給你
It’s yours if you like it.
我死了劍也帶不走
I can’t bring it with me when I die.
這個道理很少有人想得通
Not many people have got it figured out.
我想得通，所以我很快樂
I’ve figured it out, so I’m happy.
如果你想用這個方法來打動我
If you’re trying to convince me
要我救你
to help you,
那你就錯了
you’re wrong.
我知道
I know.
我不要活人的東西
I don’t want anything from anybody alive.
我只要死人的東西
All I want is something from the dead.
等你死了以後
When you’re dead,
這把劍就是我的
the sword will be mine.
你只要死人的東西？
You want something from the dead?
有些東西是死人沒有辦法給你的
There are things the dead can’t give you.
你講一樣給我聽
Name one for me.
友情
Friendship.
我不知什麼叫友情
I don’t know what friendship is.
我從來沒有朋友
I’ve never had any friends.
你們都在等我死
You’re waiting for my death.
你在等著吃我的肉
You’re waiting to eat my flesh.
你在等著拿我的劍
You’re waiting to get my sword.
可惜我死不了
But I’ll never die.
我叫衛天鵬
I’m Wei Tien-peng.
怒箭神弓斬鬼刀
The Scarier-than-the-devil Sharpshooter
跟他手下的旋風三十六刀
and his 36 Whirlwind Swordsmen.
江湖上誰不知道
Everybody knows who you are.
你有沒有看見可疑的人？
Have you seen anyone dubious?
見到一個
I’ve seen one.
誰？
Who?
我
Me.
慢著
Wait!
在他面前，你們也配動刀
How dare you use swords in front of him?
你們知道他是誰？
Do you know who he is?
他是誰？
Who is he?
卜鷹
Pu Ying.
想不到我將死的時候
Can’t believe I’ve met Pu Ying
還能見到卜鷹
before I die.
卜大公子名動天下
What is a celebrity like you
到這種地方來幹什麼？
doing here, Mr. Pu?
當然是為了三百萬兩黃金
For the three million taels of gold.
誰有那麼多黃金？
Who had so much gold?
富貴神仙呂三爺
Lu San, of course.
由鐵膽神槍鐵翼押送
It was escorted by Tieh Yi
我作接應
to be delivered to me.
想不到還是被人劫走
But it was stolen after all.
呂三爺的黃金也有人敢搶？
Who dared steal Lord Lu San’s gold?
有人敢殺呂三的獨生兒子
Someone killed his only son.
就有人敢搶呂三的三百萬兩黃金
I don’t believe nobody steals from him.
對，貓盜就敢搶
Yeah, like Cat Bandit.
何以見得是貓盜所為？
How do you know it was Cat Bandit?
鐵翼手下屍體旁邊撿到的
Found by the dead body of Tieh Yi’s man.
這就是證據
It’s the evidence.
聽說貓盜作案從來不留線索
I heard Cat Bandit never leaves anything.
這當然是故意栽贓
Someone tried to plant it on him.
卜大公子
Mr. Pu,
這片沙漠裡
the desert
已經全是呂三爺的天下
belongs to Lord Lu San.
絕沒有人能運走三百萬兩黃金
Nobody can get the gold out of here.
別忘了我是卜鷹
Remember, I’m Pu Ying.
黃金已在我手裡
If I’ve got the gold,
我就有辦法運出去
I can get it out of here.
可惜黃金不在我手裡
But I haven’t got it.
我早晚會找到證據
I’ll prove it eventually.
走
Let’s go.
想不到我居然還有朋友
Never knew I'd have a friend
不想讓我死
who doesn’t want me to die.
要命的小方也有朋友
The damned Fang has a friend?
你知道我小方哪一點要命？
Do you know why I’m damned?
你脾氣怪得要命
You’re damned eccentric.
有時好得要命
Sometimes you’re damned nice.
有時你要別人的命
Sometimes you kill people.
有時候人家要你的命
Sometimes people want to kill you.
這一次…
But this time,
你要了呂三獨生兒子的命
you killed Lu San’s only son.
不錯
You’re right.
你知道呂三爺是不會放過你的
You know Lu San will never let you go.
他有的是錢
He’s rich as hell.
而世界上偏多為錢賣命的人
And money really talks.
你為什麼要殺他兒子？
Why did you kill his son?
因為他該死
Because he deserved to die.
現在至少有十三個人來要你的命
At least 13 people are trying to kill you.
只有十三個？
Only 13?
我以為不止
I thought there’s more.
你要小心其中兩個
Beware of two of them.
一個是獨孤痴，一個是水銀
Tu-ku Chih and Shui Yin.
獨孤痴是個劍客
Tu-ku Chih is a swordsman
而水銀是個女人
while Shui Yin is a woman.
我走了
I’ve got to go.
等你死了，我會來拿這把劍
I’ll get the sword when you die.
中你魔劍，沒有立即斃命
You’ve hurt me, but I’m still alive.
不是你手下留情，就是我命大
Either you’ve shown mercy or I’m lucky.
在沙漠裡水可以救命
Water saves our lives in a desert.
這點水救不了我們的
There’s not enough water to save us.
不夠我們走出沙漠
Not enough for us to get out of the desert.
只有給我的朋友喝
But enough for my friend,
他可以帶著我們走出沙漠
who can take us out of the desert.
你的朋友？
Your friend?
牠就是我的朋友
That’s my friend.
牠始終跟著我，生死與共
We’ve been together forever.
像這樣的朋友，你有幾個？
Do you have a friend like that?
半個也沒有
Not even one.
牠是一匹千里良駒
That’s a great horse.
有了這袋水
With the water,
就可以馱著我們走出沙漠
it’ll carry us out of the desert.
你知道我是來殺你的嗎？
Do you know I’m here to kill you?
我知道
Yes, I do.
我還知道你是兩大頂尖殺手之一
And I know you’re one of the top killers,
水銀
Shui Yin.
還是留著你自己喝吧
You can keep the water.
你是不會帶水給你的敵人喝的
You’ll never give water to your enemy.
可是你也不會不帶水給自己喝
But you must have water for yourself.
這叫聰明反被聰明誤
You’re too smart for your own good.
你…你…
You...
我還是把你估得太低
I’ve underestimated you.
原來這個袋子裡才是有毒的
So it’s the poisoned water.
不是毒
Not poisoned
因為我們還不想讓你死
because we don’t want you to die now.
這是地靈水
It’s Land Spirit water,
味道跟水一樣
which tastes like water
喝下去會全身麻痺
but paralyzes you all over
接著奇渴無比
and makes you more thirsty than ever.
水…水…
Water...
給我水喝
I want water.
這水髒了，不能喝的
It’s dirty water. You can’t drink it.
（呂）
"Lu"
想不到是你救了我
Never thought you’d save me.
我救你一時
I’ve saved your life,
要活下去還得靠你自己
but it’s up to yourself to survive.
你殺了呂三爺的獨生兒子
You killed Lu San’s only son.
本來非償命不可
You had to die for it.
那現在呢？
And now?
如果你能幫我們找回
If you’ll retrieve the stolen
三百萬兩被劫黃金
three million taels of gold,
我保證呂三爺不再找你報仇
I promise that Lu San will let you go.
公平交易
It’s a fair deal.
太公平了
Very fair.
你們以為黃金一定是卜鷹劫走的
You thought Pu Ying stole the gold.
我正好認識他
I know him well.
可以替你們去辦這件事情
I can talk to him on your behalf.
是的
Yeah.
如果我不答應
If I don’t say yes,
就算你們不殺我
even if you don’t kill me,
我也會活活地渴死在沙漠裡
I’ll die of thirst in the desert.
那滋味不好受喔
It’s not an easy way to die.
哦，我是非答應不可了
So I have to say yes?
你答應了？
Is that a yes?
不答應
No.
為什麼？
Why not?
因為我不高興
Because I’m not happy.
讓他走
Let him go.
還他的劍
Return his sword.
給他一壺酒、一袋肉、一壺水
Give him some wine, meat and water.
還有…他的衣服
And... his clothes.
衛天鵬，你不聾
You’re not deaf, Wei Tien-peng.
你應該聽得見我在說什麼
You heard what I said.
卜鷹還在這個附近
Pu Ying is still around.
給你的食物和水
The food and water are enough
能維持三天
to sustain you for three days.
你找到卜鷹之後，可以再來
You can come back when you find Pu Ying.
再來？再來幹什麼？
Come back? For what?
你可以帶點消息來交換
Bring us some information for an exchange.
如果我真有消息帶來
If I’ll bring you information,
來交換的也許就不只是食物跟水
what I want won’t be just food and water.
可以
Okay.
隨便你交換什麼都行
Whatever you want.
這個女人實在是很好看的女人
That is a really good-looking woman.
#兒須成名
#You need fame
#酒須醉
#And to get drunk
#酒後傾訴
#When you’re drunk
#是真言
#You tell the truth
我知道你會來
I knew you’d come.
看起來和我第一次看見你的時候
You look completely different
風光大不相同
from when I first saw you.
有什麼不同？
How so?
現在你看起來就像個暴發戶
You look like an upstart.
我只是先預支了
I’ve advanced a part
我將要帶回去情報的一部分代價
of the information I’ll take back with me.
你想不想得到這個情報？
Do you want the information?
我非得到不可
I have to get it.
憑什麼？
With what?
本來可以憑我的劍
With my sword supposedly,
但是現在我還不想用它
but I don’t want to use it now
因為擁有這個情報的人
because I don’t know if I can defeat
劍法也許不在我之下
the man who owns the information.
你很聰明
You’re smart.
可惜聰明的人往往都不會長命
But smart guys don’t live long
因為三天以後
because in three days,
我會來替你收屍
I’ll bury you here.
（呂）
"Lu"
你是誰？
Who are you?
我叫波娃
I’m Powa.
我在等一個男人
I’m waiting for a man.
等誰？
Who?
他是個很好的人
He’s a nice man.
他姓方
His name is Fang.
你認識他？
You know him?
不認得
No.
是誰叫你來的？
Who asked you to come here?
我的主人
My master.
你的主人是誰？
Who’s your master?
他也是個男人
He’s also a man,
世上最威武強壯的男人
the strongest man in the world.
他像天空上的一隻鷹
He’s like an eagle in the sky.
卜鷹？
Pu Ying?
卜鷹
Pu Ying...
他逼走衛天鵬跟水銀
He drove off Wei Tien-peng and Shui Yin.
他為什麼要這麼做？
Why did he do that?
你一定就是我在等的人
You must be the man I’ve been waiting for.
你是個好人
You’re a nice man.
一點都沒有欺負我
You don’t take advantage of me.
我看得出來你需要什麼
I know what you need.
你要的，我都可以給你
I can give you whatever you want.
求求你不要拋下我
Please don’t leave me.
這是我第一次心甘情願的給一個男人
It’s the first time//I’m giving myself to a man willingly.
波娃這兩個字
What does
是不是有什麼特別的意義？
your name “Powa” mean?
這是藏語
It’s Tibetan.
波娃的意思就是雪
“Powa” means “snow”.
雪，多麼純潔
Snow? It’s pure and innocent.
你的名字就像你的人一樣
You’re as beautiful as your name suggests.
你的主人不是卜鷹
Your master isn’t Pu Ying.
是她
It’s her.
我敢打賭
I bet that
直到現在你一定還不相信
you would never believe
她會是這樣的女人
she’d do that to you.
衛天鵬想要你替他找回黃金
Wei Tien-peng wants you//to retrieve the stolen gold
我卻只想要你的命
while I want to kill you.
我敢打賭這次絕對沒有人來救你
I bet nobody will save you this time.
你賭什麼？
What do you bet?
賭你的命
Your life.
卜大公子又來管閒事
Mr. Pu never learns//to mind his own business.
她竟然不用回頭看
She didn’t turn back
就知道是你
to know that it’s you.
還好你沒有跟她打賭
I’m glad you didn’t make the bet,
不然你就輸了
or you would lose.
為什麼？
Why?
她說的不錯
She was right.
這一次的確沒有人要來救你
Nobody would save you this time.
你不是來救我的？
You’re not here to save me?
我只是來要你身上這五個牛皮帶
No. I just want these five belts.
碰巧我正好用得著
I happen to need them.
我要把它送給一個人
I’m giving them to someone.
送給誰？
Who?
一個自己要上吊的人
Someone who wants to hang himself.
你的劍呢？
Where’s your sword?
我不知道
I don’t know.
你不想要回你的劍嗎？
Don’t you want your sword back?
我想
Yes, I do.
其實…
In fact...
你除了這個女人之外什麼也不想要
you don’t want anything but this woman.
我不怪你，我要照顧你
I don’t blame you. I’ll take care of you.
絕不讓你受人的欺負擺佈
I won’t allow anyone to hurt you.
那邊有個商隊
There’s a caravan.
我姓方，在沙漠裡迷了路
I’m Fang, lost in the desert.
沒有水，沒有銀兩
I have no water or money.
沒有食糧
I have no food.
麻煩你們，請你們帶我們走出沙漠
Please take us out of the desert.
你什麼都沒有
You have nothing.
我為什麼要帶你走？
Why should I help you?
因為我們是人
Because we’re human beings,
你們也是人
and you are too.
而且我可以保護你們商隊的安全
And I can protect your caravan.
他姓方，我想用他
He’s Fang. I want to use him.
他有用？
He’s useful?
有
Yeah.
我來試試他有多大本事
Let’s see what he can do.
你再試試我這一刀
Another round with my dagger.
你要殺我，我就要殺你
I’ll kill you if you want to kill me.
你殺不死我，就要死在我手裡
If you can’t kill me, you’re going to die.
你說公不公平？
Is that fair?
公平
Yeah.
我不能殺你，因為你是勇士
I can’t kill you because you’re a warrior,
不怕死的勇士
a fearless warrior.
這是我們藏人最高的禮節
That’s a Tibetan’s highest etiquette
表示對你的尊敬
to show our respect to you.
你現在跟我們在一起
You’re with us now.
就要跟別人一樣，每天輪班一次
You work in shifts like everyone else.
要活下去就得做點事
You need to work to survive.
勇士是不吃閒飯的
A warrior can’t be idle at all.
看起來你們這裡勇士很多
It looks to me you have lots of warriors.
馬沙也是勇士
Masa is also a warrior.
恐怕以後永遠也看不到他了
I’m afraid you’ll never see him again.
為什麼？
Why not?
正中午的時候
At noon,
他離開商隊去解手
he left the caravan to relieve himself
就沒有回來
but didn’t come back.
找馬沙的人回來了
They went looking for Masa.
馬沙一定也回來了
I think they’re back with him.
這就怪了
That’s weird.
馬沙是個摔角的高手
Masa was a great wrestler.
他竟然…
But he was...
被人用摔角的手法活活掐死
wrestled and strangled to death.
不好了，不好了
I have bad news!
蛇鞭孫亮、金刀馬浩被殺了
Sun Liang and Ma Hao were killed!
她是我姐姐
She’s my sister.
她？那個惡毒的女人
She? That wicked woman?
我從小就跟她在一起
I’ve been with her since I was little.
她要我做什麼，我就做什麼
I did whatever she asked me to do.
你從不反抗？
You never said no?
我從來沒有想過
I never thought about it.
只要我活著
As long as I’m alive,
就沒有人再能欺負你了
nobody is going to hurt you.
你現在這麼說
You can say that to me,
可是將來…說不定你會變
but in the future, maybe you’ll change.
不管將來發生什麼事情
Whatever happens in the future,
我都不會變
I’ll never change.
你一定要相信我
You have to trust me.
我相信你
I trust you.
啊！
Ah!
這是一把寶劍
That’s a famous sword
這把劍叫魔眼
named Devil’s Eye.
殺人不沾血
It kills, never stained with blood.
只是魔眼發紅
But the devil’s eye reddens.
你一定知道這柄劍的來歷
Do you know where the sword came from?
是的，太清楚了
Yes. I know it too well
因為這柄劍是我的
because the sword is mine.
唐麟身邊使用的是峨嵋仙猿劍
Tang Lin used the Hsien Yuan Sword from E’Mei.
他出手快，而且準
He was fast and precise.
能夠殺他的人
Whoever killed him
是個出劍極快，武功高強的人
has to be faster and highly skilled.
不錯，我出劍的確不慢
You’re right. I’m fast indeed.
要殺唐麟也不難
It’s easy for me to kill Tang Lin.
只不過唐麟要是我殺的
But if I killed him,
我就不會把劍留在他身上
I wouldn’t leave my sword with him.
你的劍為什麼不在你手裡？
Why isn’t your sword with you?
我已經很久沒有看到這柄劍
I haven’t seen the sword for a long time.
我相信你
I believe you.
不過在兇手沒有查出來之前
But before we get the killer,
你還是不能夠離開
you can’t leave.
這柄劍，你也不能帶走
And you can’t take the sword away.
兇手沒有查出來之前
Before you get the killer,
就算有人趕我走，我也不會走
I won’t leave even if you drive me off.
班察巴那也不會讓你走
Bancha Bana won’t let you go.
班察巴那一回來
When Bancha Bana is back,
你也會跟他們一樣地死在沙漠上
you’ll die in the desert like they did.
班察巴那是誰？
Who’s Bancha Bana?
班察巴那！
Bancha Bana!
班察巴那回來了
Bancha Bana is back!
班察巴那！
Bancha Bana!
這是你的劍？
Is this your sword?
是的
Yes.
你就是要命的小方？
You’re the damned Fang?
是
Yes.
這一次你要被別人要命
This time, your life is threatened.
在這裡殺人，只有死
If you kill, you’ll have to die.
這麼說我是不會死的
So I won’t die then.
為什麼？
Why not?
雖然我殺過很多人
Although I’ve killed lots of people,
這一次殺人，卻正巧不是我
it was not me who killed him.
怎麼證明？
How do you prove that?
要怎麼才能證明？
What should I do to prove that?
我們藏人都相信
We Tibetans believe that
沒有罪的人是不會冤死的
an innocent person won’t die for nothing.
你先站到那邊去
Go and stand over there.
我再開始數
Then I’ll count.
數到五字，我才會出手
I’ll shoot the arrow when I count to five.
等我數到五時
When I count to five,
以你的輕功，你可走出很遠
with your kung fu,//you’ll get far away from here.
如果你真是無辜的話
If you’re really innocent,
我的箭一定射不中你
my arrow will definitely miss you.
百發百中的五花箭神
You hit the bull’s-eye almost every time.
用這種法子
Trying to see
證明一個人是不是無辜的
if someone is innocent in this way
真是個好主意
is indeed a great idea.
如果你不喜歡，還有一個法子
If you don’t like it, I have another idea.
什麼法子？
What is that?
你用這柄劍殺我
Kill me with the sword.
只要你能將我殺死
If you can kill me,
就不必再證明你是否無辜
you won’t have to prove your innocence.
兩種方法，你選哪一種？
Which one do you choose?
你可以開始數了
You can count now.
最好數快一點，我最怕久等
Count faster. I don’t like to wait.
1、2、3、4、5
One, two, three, four, five.
你不怕死？
You’re not scared to die?
我怕得要死
I’m scared of death.
你為什麼不躲？
Why didn’t you dodge?
為了證明我是無辜的
I wanted to prove that I’m innocent.
啊！
Ah!
在駝子帳篷裡
From Hunchback’s tent.
駝子，是誰幹的？
Who did this to you, Hunchback?
駝子
Hunchback?
想不到…想不到…
I’ve never thought...
想不到什麼？
Never thought what?
想不到殺人的竟是他
Never thought he was the killer.
他是誰？
Who is he?
他…　-到哪去了？
He...　- Where is he?
他…他…
He...
想不到殺人的竟是你
I’ve never thought you were the killer.
想不到是你
It was you.
帶我走，求求你帶我走
Please. Get me out of here.
我一定會帶你走的
I’ll get you out of here.
誰也不能帶她走
Nobody gets her out of here.
為什麼？
Why not?
我說過在這裡殺人的，只有死
I told you whoever kills here must die.
你應該看得出來殺人的不是她
But it wasn’t she who killed him.
那你一定看得出殺人的是誰了？
So you know who killed him?
是他
He did.
你可知道這些貨物
Do you know which caravan
是哪一個商隊的？
these goods belong to?
這跟殺人有什麼關係？
What has it got to do with killing?
這些貨，這裡的人都是鷹記
These goods and men belong to Ying’s.
飛鷹的鷹？
Pu Ying?
對
Yes.
你就是他們的東主
You’re their owner?
就是他，連收容你、信任你
He is. He even asked us
都是我們東主吩咐的
to take you in and trust you,
否則你早已死在我的箭下
or I would’ve killed you with my arrows.
你總不會相信他搜自己的貨物
You think he would search his goods
殺自己的人吧
and kill his men?
誰也沒有看到殺人的是她
But nobody saw her kill him.
可誰也不能證明她是無辜的
Nobody can prove her innocence either.
你又要用那種方法來證明？
Are you going to prove it in that way?
對
Yes.
五花箭神的箭絕不會傷及無辜
The arrows will never hurt the innocent.
你雖然說過
Although you said that
只要你活著
as long as you’re alive,
就不會讓別人來欺負我
you won’t allow anyone to hurt me,
可是我早就知道這是做不到的
I know you can’t keep your promise.
每件事都會改變
Everything changes.
每個人都會變
Everybody changes.
現在你可以忘記這些話
Just forget what you’ve said
就讓他們殺了我
and let them kill me.
讓她走
Let her go.
就這樣讓她走？
Just like her go like that?
當然不是
Of course not.
還得給她一袋水、一袋食糧
Give her some water, food
一匹最快的馬
and the fastest horse.
我要她走得越快越好
I want her to leave as soon as possible.
她走，你留下
She goes. You stay.
這是條件？
Is that your condition?
是
Yes.
你走吧
Just go.
只要我不死，我一定會去找你
As long as I’m alive, I’ll find you.
你也一定能夠找到我
And I believe you’ll find me.
你既然肯放她走
You let her go.
為什麼要我留下？
Why do I have to stay?
你受傷了？
You’re hurt?
只要是人都會受傷
Anybody could get hurt.
可是江湖上都知道
But we all know that
你是從來不敗的
you’ve never been defeated.
每一件事都有第一次
There’s always a first time//for everything.
你已經跟他交過手了？
You’ve already fought with him?
我在衛天鵬的帳篷裡見過他
I saw him in Wei Tien-peng’s tent.
無名無姓，像個孤魂野鬼
He has no name, like a ghost.
難怪駝子也會遭到暗算
No wonder Hunchback got assassinated.
當代七大劍客當中
None of the top seven swordsmen
也沒有人能接得住他這一劍
can take a blow from him.
必殺、必勝、必死的絕劍
He holds the invincible sword.
可是…你還沒有死
But you’re still alive.
你怎麼曉得，我留下你…
Who knows? I asked you to stay...
也許我要讓你等我死
Maybe I want you to watch me die.
因為我也曾經等你死
I did that to you once after all.
我等你，不是等你死
I’m not waiting to watch you die,
而是等你站起來
but for you to stand up.
有一件事我要告訴你
I need to tell you something.
那個無名劍客
The unknown swordsman
並不是真的沒有名字
doesn’t really have no name.
他姓獨孤，叫獨孤痴
His name is Tu-ku Chih.
他不是痴於情
He’s not crazy for love,
而是痴於劍
but crazy for swords.
痴於情的人
Someone crazy for love will
一定會死在痴於劍的劍下
be killed by someone crazy for swords.
這一點你不能不信
You have to believe that.
你為什麼要對我說這些話？
Why are you telling me these?
因為你是我的朋友
Because you’re my friend.
有客人來了
The guests are here.
主人為什麼還不出來？
Where is the host?
卜大老闆的架子未免太大了吧
Boss Pu really knows how to put on frills.
我的架子本來就不小
Yes, I do indeed.
這是玉女天魔柳分分
That’s Liu Fen-fen.
那個瞎子就是搜魂手
The blind man is Soul Snatcher.
主人既然不出來
The host refuses to come out,
我們何不闖進去
why don’t we barge in?
你們想要怎麼樣？
What do you want?
三百萬兩黃金跟一個人
Three million taels of gold and a man.
黃金不在我這裡，不能給你
I don’t have the gold and can’t give you.
人在我這裡
I have the man
更不能給你
but can’t give you either.
黃金在，人也在
You have both the gold and the man.
你們的人昨天已經來找過了
Your cohorts came yesterday
應該知道黃金不在貨物裡
to find that we don’t have the gold.
也沒有那麼大的地方可以藏黃金
Neither do we have so much space for it.
除了你貓盜之外
Nobody but you, Cat Bandit,
沒有人能從鐵翼手下
could steal the gold
劫走那批黃金
from Tieh Yi.
衛天鵬
Wei Tien-peng,
你這樣子，他是不會承認的
he’ll never admit it.
你有辦法叫他承認？
Can you make him do that?
法子很古老，也很俗氣
I know a traditional and dumb way,
可是最有效
but it’s effective.
勝者為強，敗者遭殃
The winner stays while the loser goes.
如果他敗在我們手裡
If we defeat him,
就算不是他們劫走的
even when he didn’t steal it,
也得交出三百萬兩黃金
he’ll have to give us the gold.
這法子好像還不錯
It sounds like a good idea.
要卜大老闆交出三百萬兩黃金
It’s easy for Boss Pu to give us
似乎不難
three million taels of gold.
我們三陣賭輸贏
We’ll fight three rounds
就賭那三百萬兩黃金
for the three million taels of gold
和那個人
and that man.
我是小方
I’m Fang,
就是你們要找的人
the man that you’re here for.
是不是現在就動手？
Are we going to fight now?
他根本不是來找你這個人
He’s not here for you.
這是他們的戰略
That’s their strategy.
戰略？
Strategy?
因為他們知道我受傷
They know that I’ve been hurt.
你不必太難過
Don’t be upset.
能在獨孤痴劍下保存生命的
I believe that you’re the only one
除了你之外，還沒有第二個人
who survived Tu-ku Chih’s sword.
這就是我另外一隻手
This is another arm of mine.
也叫魔手
It’s called Magic Arm.
裡面藏有十七種暗器
There are 17 hidden weapons
還有七種殺人的利器
and seven deadly weapons in it.
我也有另外一隻手
I have another arm too.
你也有另外一隻手？
You have another arm?
在哪裡？
Where is it?
你兩隻手全在這裡
Both your arms are right there.
你想看？
You want to see it?
想得很
Yes, of course.
看清楚
Watch closely.
我的雙手跟別人也沒有什麼兩樣
My arms aren’t different from others’.
這算什麼？
What the hell?
算你敗
You’ve lost.
三仗，你輸了一仗
You’ve lost the first round.
你們以二比一
That was two against one.
我動也沒有動過
But I didn’t move at all.
出手的是他
It was him who fought you.
我又沒有對你說過…
I never told you
我另外一隻手在我身上
that other arm belongs to me.
三仗已經輸了兩仗
You’ve lost two rounds.
是不是還要比下去？
Are we going to keep fighting?
無論鬥智鬥力
Nobody can outsmart
卜大老闆無人能及
or outfight Boss Pu.
但是智者千慮，也難免會有失
But you can never//take everything into account.
我只要一聲令下
With my order,
片刻間他們就衝過來
they’ll charge in an instant.
我要這裡橫屍遍地
And you’ll all be dead.
最好你能夠睜開眼睛看一看
I wish you could open your eyes and see.
可惜你是個瞎子
Unfortunately, you’re blind.
衛天鵬，下令
Give an order, Wei Tien-peng!
你們動手啊
Why don’t you do anything?
想不到呂三爺手下最好的幾位高手
It seems that Lu San’s best men
連同旋風三十六刀
and the 36 Whirlwind Swordsmen
都要埋葬沙漠
will be buried in the desert.
你們一動手
If you move,
我就刺死轎子裡面的人
I’ll kill the lady in the sedan chair.
波娃
Powa?
讓他們走吧
Just let them go.
讓他們走
Let them go.
只要我不死，我一定會殺你
As long as I’m alive, I’ll kill you.
你為了我
For me,
失去了一個殲敵的大好機會
you’ve lost a chance to kill them.
不全是為了你
Not just for you.
#烈日當空
#The scorching sun high up
#征程茫茫
#The journey ahead unknown
#大地一飛鷹，重重越關山
#An eagle is flying over the mountains
前面的出口兩邊山岩都有人
People are lying in ambush//on the both sides of the exit.
可能是呂三的人埋伏在那
I think they’re sent by Lu San.
#滿天風沙
#Blowing sand everywhere
#長途流浪
#Roving about endlessly
#不知天涯在何方
#Never know where I belong
我們是退回去，還是衝過去？
Are we turning around or charging ahead?
卜鷹，我好想你
Pu Ying! I miss you so much!
班察巴那，我好想你們喔
Bancha Bana! I miss you all!
她是誰？
Who’s that?
她姓藍，名叫陽光
She’s Lan Yang-kuang.
我本來想嚇唬你們
I planned to scare you.
可是我又怕真的把你給嚇死了
But I didn’t want to scare you to death.
像你這麼好的人
I’ll never find
天下再也找不到第二個
another man as nice as you.
哎，要是真的把你嚇死了
What if I really scared you
那可怎麼辦
to death?
你答應過我不要亂跑
You promised me to stay put.
為什麼又跑出來？
What are you doing here?
你為什麼總喜歡捏我的鼻子？
Why do you always pinch my nose?
你是不是想把我的鼻子
Do you want to make my nose
捏得跟你一樣
look like yours?
他是誰？
Who’s that?
他叫小方，要命的小方
He’s Fang, the damned Fang.
為什麼叫他要命的小方呢？
Why do you call him the damned Fang?
因為他跟你一樣要命
Because he’s damned like you,
有時候把人嚇死，有時候把人氣死
either scares or upsets people to death.
而他自己卻是個偏偏不要命的人
But he’s never afraid to be killed.
我喜歡不要命的男人
I like a man unafraid to be killed.
現在我開始喜歡你了
I’m beginning to like you.
卜鷹的朋友，就是我的朋友
Pu Ying’s friends are my friends.
卜鷹喜歡的人，我都喜歡
I like whoever Pu Ying likes.
我也喜歡你
I like you too.
真的喜歡你
I really do.
我叫齊小燕，請你跟我走
I’m Chi Hsiao-yen. Please come with me.
跟你走，為什麼？
Go with you? Why?
因為有一個朋友叫我來找你
A friend asked me to find you here.
我已經在這裡等你一夜了
I’ve waited for you all night.
你知道我是誰？
You know who I am?
我當然知道，你姓方
Of course I do. You’re Fang.
別人都叫你要命的小方
People call you the damned Fang.
你怎麼知道我在這裡？
How do you know that I’m here?
全拉薩城的人都知道你來了
All the people in Lhasa know you’re here.
我那個朋友是誰？
Who’s the friend?
我不能說
I can’t tell you.
為什麼？
Why not?
因為他要我替他守秘密
He asked me to keep it a secret.
我已經答應他了
And I promised him.
就算你殺了我，我也不會說出來的
I won’t tell you even if you kill me.
好，我跟你去
Okay. I’ll go with you.
走
Let’s go.
這些都是我做的
I’ve made all these.
你看得出這些鳥籠…
Do you know how
有什麼特別的地方？
these birdcages are unique?
鳥籠的門全都開著
The doors are all open,
而且裡面沒有鳥
and there’s no bird inside.
鳥都飛了
The birds flew away
因為我不願牠們當囚犯
because I don’t want to imprison them.
只要牠們高興，隨時都可以飛出去
They can fly away whenever they want,
可是飛走的往往又會飛回來
but they’ll come back eventually
因為我是牠們的朋友
because I’m their friend.
你的朋友在裡面
Your friend’s in there.
我是小方，我來了
I’m Fang. I’m here.
坐
Sit down.
是你
It’s you.
是我
It’s me.
你一定想不到是我找你來
You’d never think//it was me who asked for you.
我是沒想到
You’re right.
我找你來是因為我沒有朋友
I asked for you because I have no friends.
你雖然不是我的朋友
Although you’re not my friend,
但是我知道你一定會來
I knew you’d come.
你應該看得出
You can see that
我這隻手是被人捏碎的
someone grasped my hand and broke it.
只有一個人能捏碎我的手
Only one man can break my hand.
卜鷹，他不是劍客，也不是英雄
Pu Ying. He isn’t a swordsman or hero.
他是個人傑
He’s an outstanding man.
他的心中只有勝，沒有敗
He knows only victory, not defeat.
只許勝，不許敗
He allows only victory, not defeat.
為求勝
In order to win,
他故意讓我的劍刺入他的胸膛
he guided my sword to stab into his chest.
就在這一霎那
In that instant,
他毀了我這隻握劍的手
he broke my sword-holding hand.
我看得出你雖然失去了握劍的手
I can see that without the hand,
但心中仍然充滿劍氣
you still wield the sword in your mind.
所以我才找你來
That’s what I want from you.
你要我殺卜鷹？
You want me to kill Pu Ying?
不是
No.
我要你去為我殺一個該殺的人
I want you to kill someone//who deserve to die.
誰？
Who?
波娃
Powa.
波娃？
Powa?
為什麼？
Why?
如今我是個無用的廢人
I’ve been maimed.
知道秘密又太多
And I know too many secrets.
胡氏那班人絕不是我的對手
Hu and his men will never defeat me.
所以呂三派波娃主持殺我
That’s why Lu San sent Powa to kill me.
波娃會武功？
Powa knows martial arts?
波娃用不著武功
She doesn’t have to.
魅力就是她的武器
She uses her charms as her best weapon.
她可以指使任何人來殺我
She can make anyone kill me.
我不答應
I can’t do that.
你不能不答應
You have to.
波娃跟那三百萬兩黃金有關
Powa is related to the stolen gold.
要命的小方一向不要錢
The damned Fang never wants money.
為什麼會突然改變
Why do you change your mind
對那些黃金這麼關心？
and take the stolen gold to heart?
（鷹記商號）
"Ying’s Trading"
謝謝
Thank you.
普松喇嘛在等你，等你很久了
Puson Lama has been waiting for you.
普松喇嘛？
Puson Lama?
布達拉宮裡面最受人敬仰的喇嘛
The most respected lama//in the Potala Palace.
我就是方偉，你找我何事？
I’m Fang Wei. How can I help you?
要知道我為什麼來找你
If you want to know how you can help me,
你就跟我來
just come with me.
我要找你，因為我要你死
I visited you because I want to kill you.
剛才我已經知道
I’ve found that
你是有名的劍客，現在手裡沒有劍
you’re a famous swordsman without a sword.
我殺人不用劍，而用手
I kill with my hands, not a sword.
我的手卻還在
But I have my hands here.
看來是這樣
I can see that.
所以我不會死，你會死
So I won’t die, but you will.
你的劍？
Your sword...
在我心裡，這是一把心劍
It’s a sword in my heart.
波…波娃
Powa...
是不是波娃叫你來殺我的？
Did Powa ask you to kill me?
對，修道數十年
Yes. I’ve been a lama for years.
我自認已經摒棄七情六慾
I thought I’d been ridden of all desires.
沒有想到一見到她
But when I saw her,
就無法控制自己
I couldn’t control myself.
她要我帶你去見她
She asked me to bring you to her.
我寧可死也不願帶你去
But I’d rather die than do that.
我活著時，誰也不能把她搶去
When I’m alive, nobody can steal her away.
想不到你居然沒有死
I didn’t expect you to live.
我要普松去找你
I asked Puson to find you
並不是為了要你來看我
not that I wanted you to see me,
而是為了要你的命
but that I wanted to kill you.
難得你還會說真話
You’re finally telling me the truth.
普松不會讓你來看我
Puson wouldn’t allow you to see me.
如果他不能殺你
If he couldn’t kill you,
就必定會死在你的手裡
you would kill him.
你殺了普松
If you killed Puson,
噶倫喇嘛一定會殺你報仇
Kalon Lama would kill you
他們的關係就好像父子般親密
because they’re like father and son.
可是他並沒有殺我
But he didn’t kill me.
所以我還是算錯了一點
That’s where I was wrong.
噶倫喇嘛比我想像的…
Kalon Lama is smarter
更精明、更能幹
and more capable than I expected.
他看穿了我的用心
He saw through my calculation.
我低估了他對我的痛恨
I underestimated his hatred for me.
他寧可放過你
He’d rather let you go
也不會讓我稱心如意
than give me what I want.
你為什麼要告訴我這些？
Why are you telling me these?
因為我已經沒有辦法再騙你了
Because I can’t keep telling you lies.
你為什麼要這麼做？
Why did you do that?
我們是仇敵，我只有想法子殺你
You’re my enemy. I have to kill you.
噶倫喇嘛稀世的銹劍
The rare rusted sword of Kalon Lama.
讓人相信被這把銹劍殺死的人
It’s said that those killed by it
萬劫不能復生
would never go into reincarnation.
但是你殺了我，我也絕不怪你
But I won’t blame you if you kill me.
你殺不殺我都好，我不勉強你
It’s all right if you kill me or not.
但是我一定要提醒你
But I need to remind you that
你不殺我，就有人會殺你
if you don’t kill me, you’ll be killed.
我知道
I know.
噶倫喇嘛可以在舉手之間
Kalon Lama can kill you
置你於死地
in a blink.
我也知道
Yeah, I know.
名劍如良駒
Like a great horse,
你不能善用它，就應該還給我
if you can’t use the sword well,//just give it back to me.
你想殺我
You want to kill me?
難道你忘了我是什麼人？
Don’t you remember who I am?
你忘了我們之間的密約？
Remember our secret agreement?
我沒有忘
Yes, I do.
那麼你就應該知道
Then you should know that
如果你殺了我
if you kill me,
你不但後悔終生
you’ll be regretful forever
你的罪孽也就永遠沒辦法洗清
and won’t be purged of your sins.
你卻不知道我不能不殺你
But you don’t know that I have to kill you
因為普松是我的兒子
because Puson was my real son.
二十八年前
28 years ago,
我也遇過像你這樣的女人
I also met a woman like you.
如今連我兒子的生命也賠上
Now my son was killed because of you.
卜鷹？
Pu Ying?
恭喜大師
Congratulations.
大師已從劍中悟道
You’ve got the realization from the sword.
我知道你心中還有一個打不開的結
I know there’s still a knot in your heart.
能夠打開這個結的人
And I’m the only one
只有我
who can untie it.
呂爺，你都看到了
You saw it, Lord Lu.
嗯，我都看到，也都聽見
Yes. I saw it and heard it.
普松已經喪命
Puson was killed.
噶倫喇嘛已經悟禪
Kalon Lama has got the realization.
不會再理布達拉宮的政事
He’ll leave the Potala Palace forever.
控制布達拉宮，也就是控制西藏
If you get the Palace, you own Tibet.
布達拉宮內
In the Potala Palace,
再也沒有能阻撓三爺的人
nobody will impede you, my Lord.
自命不凡的卜鷹，他萬萬沒有想到
That self-complacent Pu Ying won’t believe
他派到我這來臥底的女人
that the woman working undercover for him
會反他反得那麼徹底
would rebel against him.
在我呂三爺面前
In front of me,
他不過是一個平凡的人
he’s nobody.
倉庫禁地，任何人不能進來
You can’t go into the storeroom.
卜鷹帶我來的
Pu Ying brought me here.
他說他家裡我到處都可以走
He said I can walk around at will.
回去
Get out!
這裡例外
It’s an exception.
這裡也不例外
It’s no exception.
讓小方進來
Let him in.
現在你可以相信
Now you believe
三百萬兩黃金並不在我手中
that I don’t have the stolen gold.
但這並不能證明…
But you can’t prove
你沒有劫走那批黃金
that you didn’t steal the gold.
你很細心
You’re scrupulous.
不愧是大明邊疆的巡察使
You’re indeed a competent frontier inspector//from the Ming court.
上次在沙漠裡看見你的時候
When I saw you in the desert last time,
我就開始懷疑你
I began to suspect you.
以你這麼一個身經百戰的高手
Having been experienced,
不可能在匆忙的情況下
you would never enter a desert
帶不足的糧食和水
without enough food and water
貿然進入沙漠
in such a hurry
因為人人都知道
because everyone knows that
在沙漠裡渴死
dying of thirst in a desert is worse
遠比死在敵人的亂刀下痛苦
than being killed by your enemies’ swords.
所以你一直跟著我，考驗我
That’s why you followed and tested me,
你並不是真的要等我死，拿我的劍
not to wait for my death and sword.
很久以後我才領悟到
I realized after a long while
你就是大明邊疆巡察使
that you’re the frontier inspector.
為了阻止呂三
In order to stop Lu San from
用黃金支援元朝的餘黨
supporting the Yuan remnants with gold,
故意困在沙漠中，讓他們抓到你
you deliberately got yourself//stuck and caught in the desert
以便打聽黃金的秘密
to find out the secrets about the gold.
說不定你殺死呂三的兒子
Maybe you killed Lu San’s son
唯一的理由就是讓他們追捕你
just to get them to hunt you down.
你到底是什麼人？
Who the hell are you?
我就是卜鷹
I’m Pu Ying,
一個平凡的西藏人
an ordinary Tibetan
懷念西藏依附中原的盛世
nostalgic for the past prosperity
不讓呂三統治西藏
who doesn’t want Lu San to rule Tibet.
既然不是你
If you didn’t do it,
還有誰能搶這批黃金？
who would steal the gold?
黃金是我搶的
I stole the gold,
不過不藏在這裡
but it’s not hidden here.
卜鷹，你真是個對敵人捨身求勝
You show no mercy on your enemies,
對朋友捨生取義的人傑
but you’re loyal to friends.
不過要做你的朋友，有時候很難
But it’s not easy to be your friend.
呂三運三百萬兩黃金到拉薩的消息
Powa told me Lu San was about to transport
就是波娃洩漏給我的
three million taels of gold to Lhasa.
波娃怎麼會知道？
How did she know that?
她是我派出埋伏在呂三身邊的人
She worked undercover for me.
劫來的黃金就埋在沙漠
The stolen gold is buried in the desert.
一望無際的沙漠
The desert is vast and limitless.
你怎麼認得出來？
How can you recognize the burial site?
因為我血管裡流的是沙
Because sand is flowing in my veins
沙漠是我的根
and the desert is my root.
我還有什麼地方認不出來的
I can recognize it at a glance.
#烈日當空
#The scorching sun high up
#征程茫茫
#The journey ahead unknown
#大地一飛鷹，重重越關山
#An eagle is flying over the mountains
#滿天風沙
#Blowing sand everywhere
#長途流浪
#Roving about endlessly
#不知天涯在何方
#Never know where I belong
三百萬兩黃金都在這裡
The three million taels of gold is here.
巡察使，你現在準備怎麼辦？
What do we do now, Inspector?
只要黃金不在蒙古人手裡
As long as the Moguls don’t have the gold
元朝餘黨無法再進犯中原
and the Yuan remnants can’t invade us,
我的任務就算完成一半
my mission is half completed.
另一半呢？
What about the other half?
要看黃金落在誰手裡
It depends on who gets the gold.
落在我的手裡
It’s in my hands.
在一代人傑手裡
In the hand of an outstanding man,
一定可以造福西藏老百姓
it’ll do the Tibetans good.
我們被跟蹤了
We’ve been followed.
他不怕有人跟蹤
He’s not afraid of being followed
因為他知道這一路我都在你們附近
because he knows that I’ve been around.
就算有狐狸跟蹤，我早就抓到他
If a fox followed you, I’d catch him
剝他的皮
and skin him alive.
可是你們就沒發現我這隻狐狸
But you’ve missed this fox.
陽光
Yang-kuang?
我要她送你一程
I asked her to see you off.
對，我也得趕回京城，奏請朝廷
Yeah. I have to go back to the capital
通令全國捉拿呂三
and asked the emperor to arrest Lu San.
我留在這裡，一方面守著黃金
I’ll stay here to guard the gold
一方面注意呂三在拉薩的勢力
and monitor Lu San in Lhasa.
再說
Besides...
你路不熟，在路上你必須要有個伴
you’re a stranger here. You need company.
卜鷹為什麼要你送得那麼遠？
Why did Pu Ying ask you to see me off?
我也不知道
I don’t know.
你是他什麼人？
Who are you to him?
我是他未婚妻，我們已經有了婚約
I’m his fiancée. We’re engaged.
他一直不讓你知道這件事
He didn’t want you to know that
他認為你很喜歡我
because he knew you like me.
而且他一直覺得自己老了
And he always thinks that
配不上我
he’s too old for me.
所以…
So...
所以他才讓你送我，送到江南
he wants you to come with me to the south.
他就是這樣一個人
That’s how he has always been.
總是替別人著想
He does everything for others,
從不替自己想想
never for himself.
可是他的外表卻偏偏冷得像冰一樣
But he looks as cold as ice.
這些事他寧死都不會對你說
He’ll never tell you because
因為他不願意讓你心裡有負擔
he doesn’t want you to feel pressured
不願意讓你感激他
or like you owe him something.
不管他怎麼對我
Whatever he does to me,
我對他都不會變的
I’ll always be loyal to him.
所以不管到什麼地方
So wherever you go,
你都一定會回去的
you’ll go back to him eventually.
你明白我的意思？
You know what I mean?
我當然明白
Of course I do.
我知道他沒有看錯你
I knew he was right.
你的確是他的朋友
You’re his best friend indeed.
柳分分
Liu Fen-fen?
不要動她！
Don’t touch her!
為什麼？
Why?
這是一個陷阱
It’s a trap.
你只要一動她
If you touch her,
他們就會知道我們經過這
they’ll know we’ve been here.
他們是誰？
Who do you mean?
呂三用黃金收買的人
The people bribed by Lu San with gold.
柳分分也是他們的人
Liu Fen-fen is also one of them.
為什麼要這樣對付她？
Why did they do this to her?
呂三利用她來引誘我們中他的圈套
Lu San uses her to lure us into his trap
同時也是在懲罰她
and punishes her at the same time.
我們走吧
Let’s go.
既然你不能救她，又不忍心殺她
Since you can’t save her or kill her,
為什麼不肯走呢？
why don’t you just go?
再不走他們的人就快來了
They’ll be here anytime.
他們還沒走
They’re still around.
我看他們是永遠跟定了
I don’t think they’ll leave us.
這個泥娃娃
The clay doll
是他特地從無錫帶回來的
was brought by him from Wuxi.
你這麼喜歡江南的東西
You love what’s from the south.
等到了京城以後
When we’re in the capital,
我帶你去吃江南的桂花糕、荷葉糖
I’ll buy you osmanthus cakes//and lotus leaf candy.
沒有到過江南的人
Those who have never been to the south
都會想到江南去
want to go there.
可是到了江南，我會想念拉薩
But when I’m there, I’ll miss Lhasa.
拉薩？
Lhasa?
是卜鷹，還是拉薩？
Pu Ying or Lhasa?
我有一種很滑稽的想法
I have a funny idea.
我現在正在做卜鷹曾經做過的事情
I’m doing what Pu Ying did once.
在這小木屋裡跟你促膝相對
Talking to you in this cabin
跟你喝酒
and drinking with you.
我們曾經在這裡醉過三天三夜
We got drunk here//for three nights and days.
這酒好香
The wine tastes great.
今天天氣真不錯
The weather is fine.
你想不想出去走走？
Do you want to take a walk?
我不去，你去，我在這等你
No. You go ahead. I’ll be waiting here.
我一個人去，很快就回來
I’ll go alone. Be right back.
我回來得快不快？
Am I back soon enough?
快極了
More than enough.
這條路也不通，你還是回去吧
It’s a dead end. Go back now.
這一年內你休想走出小木屋一步
You’ll stay in the cabin for a year.
你受傷了沒有？
Are you hurt?
沒有，因為他們根本不想要我的命
No. They didn’t even want to kill me.
如果想呢？
What if they did?
那我已經是個死人了
Then I’d be dead.
時候不早了，不如早點睡吧
It’s late. Let’s go to bed.
好，你睡床，我睡地板
Yeah. The bed is yours.//I’ll sleep on the floor.
我睡床，你也睡床
I’ll sleep on the bed, and you too.
好
Okay.
你睡床，我也睡床
You’ll sleep on the bed, and me too.
我有一個想法
I have an idea.
他們不想殺死你
They didn’t want to kill you.
只想逼你跟我睡上床
But they’re forcing you to sleep with me.
而且他們都有偷窺狂
And they’re all peeping Toms.
可是又不肯躲在窗縫裡偷看
But they refuse to peep through a window.
乾脆把屋頂、牆壁都拆了
So they tore up the roof and walls.
你曾經積過什麼陰德？
What good have you done
讓這麼多人肯為你安排…
to make all those people arrange
這麼美好的一件事
such a beautiful thing for you?
我把富貴神仙呂三的獨生兒子宰掉
I killed Lu San’s only son.
那呂三為什麼不殺了你
Then why didn’t he kill you
替他兒子報仇呢？
to seek his revenge on you?
呂三要你跟我生兒子
Lu San wants you to give me a son.
再殺我的兒子
Then he’ll kill my son.
也讓我嘗嘗喪子之痛
He wants me to grieve for it too.
怪不得那個追風叟
No wonder Wind Chaser
要你在這裡待上一年
ordered you to stay here for a year.
他大概是想在這一年之內
He wants us to give birth
我們總有辦法生出個兒子吧
to a son within the year.
如果我是個天生不育的男人
If I was born infertile,
那呂三這個計畫
Lu San’s plan
一輩子也成功不了了
will never work.
繼續笑，我們快離開這裡，回拉薩
Keep laughing. Let’s get out of here//and go back to Lhasa.
想卜鷹？
You miss Pu Ying?
對，呂三派這麼多人看住我們
Yeah. Lu San has sent so many people here.
也會派更多的人去拜訪卜鷹
He must’ve sent more to visit Pu Ying.
拼命也要離開這裡
We have to get out of here.
讓我來想個辦法
I’ll figure out a way.
看得清楚在幹嘛？
Can you see what she’s doing?
看不大清楚，她在幹什麼？
No. What is she doing?
老色鬼，她在解手，看得還不夠？
Old letch! She’s relieving herself.//Have you seen enough?
卜大老闆
Hi, Boss Pu.
我們的人呢？
Where are our men?
都被我的屬下高手消滅了
They were all killed by my men.
卜鷹，現在該輪到你
Pu Ying, it’s your turn now.
我的三百萬兩黃金藏在什麼地方？
Where is my three million taels of gold?
我知道你一定不會告訴我
I know you won’t tell me.
你的確很聰明
You’re smart indeed.
我怎麼也沒想到
I never thought that
你會藏在鐵翼的屍體下
you’d hide it under Tieh Yi’s dead body.
黃金我找到了
I’ve got the gold.
也就是你該死的時候
And it’s time to kill you.
貓盜畢竟是人，在我的逼供之下
Cat Bandit is human after all.
他還是說出來了
He was put to torture and confessed.
他一定還活著
He must be alive.
阿蘇喇嘛
Asu Lama?
火熄了
The fire burned out.
我就來這裡，只找到這些骨灰
I’m here to find the bone ash.
是誰的骨灰？
Whose bone ash?
這裡有我的族人、我的朋友
I have my people and my friends here.
我也想知道是誰的骨灰
I want to know who’s who,
可惜每個人都已成了灰
but they were burned to ashes.
還有誰能夠分辨得出？
Who can tell who’s who?
是誰的骨灰？
Whose bone ash?
阿蘇，連你們都被收買了
You’ve been bribed too, Asu.
說，呂三到底在哪？
Tell me. Where is Lu San?
我要卜鷹死，卜鷹已經死了
I wanted Pu Ying to die, and he’s dead.
我呂三爺要要命的小方
I want the damned Fang
也嘗一嘗喪子之痛
to grieve for the loss of his son.
現在他跟他女朋友果然來了
And he’s here with his girlfriend.
也許他們是想在我這棟金宮裡
Maybe they’ll give birth to a son
生一個金童
in my golden palace.
班察巴那
Bancha Bana!
卜鷹呢？
Where’s Pu Ying?
我最後看到他的時候
When I last saw him,
他已陷在火焰中
he was stuck in the flames.
卜鷹死了？
Pu Ying is dead?
班察巴那可以從火中逃走
I managed to escape from the fire.
卜鷹是班察巴那的主人
Pu Ying is my master.
卜鷹更不會死
I don’t think he died.
現在會死的
Who’s going to die now...
只有呂三
...is Lu San.
波娃還給你
Powa is yours now.
班察巴那，她一直是你的女人
Bancha Bana, she has been your woman.
現在你可以把她帶走
You can take her away.
陽光
Yang-kuang?
Yang-kuang!
陽光
Yang-kuang?
小方，把陽光送回卜鷹的懷抱
Fang, escort Yang-kuang back to Pu Ying,
把三百萬兩黃金運回大明朝
and the stolen gold to the court.
（劇終）
"The End"